<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>U.S. Geological Survey - Alaska Science Center</origin>
        <origin>National Park Service - Southwest Alaska Inventory and Monitoring Network</origin>
        <origin>University of Alaska Fairbanks - College of Fisheries and Ocean Sciences</origin>
        <pubdate>20160930</pubdate>
        <title>Intertidal Temperature Data from Kachemak Bay, Prince William Sound, Katmai National Park and Preserve, and Kenai Fjords National Park</title>
        <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>Intertidal Temperature Data from Kachemak Bay, Prince William Sound, Katmai National Park and Preserve, and Kenai Fjords National Park</sername>
          <issue>ver 4.0, September 2023</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Anchorage, Alaska</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <othercit>Suggested Citation: U.S. Geological Survey - Alaska Science Center, National Park Service - Southwest Alaska Inventory and Monitoring Network, and University of Alaska Fairbanks - College of Fisheries and Ocean Sciences, 2016. Intertidal temperature data from Kachemak Bay, Prince William Sound, Katmai National Park and Preserve, and Kenai Fjords National Park (ver 4.0, September 2023): U.S. Geological Survey data release, https://doi.org/10.5066/F7WH2N3T</othercit>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/F7WH2N3T</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</origin>
            <pubdate>2005</pubdate>
            <title>Nearshore Marine Ecosystem Research Program</title>
            <geoform>website</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>Alaska Science Portal</sername>
              <issue>99</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Anchorage, Alaska</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>This is a link to the broader USGS Alaska Science Center research project supported by these data. Users will find a description of the research project and links to associated reports, publications, and data products.</othercit>
            <onlink>https://alaska.usgs.gov/portal/project.php?project_id=99</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>These data are part of the Gulf Watch Alaska (GWA) long-term monitoring program. This dataset consists of date, time, and temperature measurements from intertidal rocky sampling sites, including predicted tide height at the time of the reading, which is used to distinguish air from water temperature readings. The data are provided as comma separated values (.csv) files derived from data downloaded from HOBO temperature loggers.</abstract>
      <purpose>The purpose of this dataset is to document intertidal water and air temperatures at rocky intertidal study sites. Sampling was conducted in rocky intertidal habitats within each of the GWA regions: Kenai Peninsula (KEFJ), Katmai (KATM), Kachemak Bay (KBAY) and Prince William Sound (NPWS. EPWS, and WPWS). The purpose of rocky intertidal sampling is to assess change in intertidal invertebrate and algal communities in sheltered rocky habitats.</purpose>
      <supplinf>This versioned data release supersedes two previous nearshore temperature USGS data releases (https://doi.org/10.5066/F7WH2N3T and https://doi.org/10.5066/F77S7KXH). The data provided in this release includes all data from past releases as well as new data collected after 2017 for KBAY, KEFJ, WPWS, and KATM. This data release will continue to be updated as new data are collected each sampling year.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>2006</begdate>
          <enddate>2023</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>observed</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>In work</progress>
      <update>Annually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <descgeog>Prince William Sound, Kachemak Bay, Kenai Fjords National Park, and Katmai National Park and Preserve.</descgeog>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-156.643</westbc>
        <eastbc>-145.415</eastbc>
        <northbc>61.122</northbc>
        <southbc>57.938</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Metadata Identifier</themekt>
        <themekey>USGS:ASC463</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>Biota</themekey>
        <themekey>Environment</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>NASA GCMD Earth Science Keyword Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Atmospheric/Ocean Indicators</themekey>
        <themekey>Temperature indicators</themekey>
        <themekey>Temperature trends</themekey>
        <themekey>Temperature variability</themekey>
        <themekey>Ocean heat budget</themekey>
        <themekey>Biospheric indicators</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS CSA Biocomplexity Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Air temperature</themekey>
        <themekey>Ocean temperature</themekey>
        <themekey>Intertidal environments</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>Coastal ecosystems</themekey>
        <themekey>Marine ecosystems</themekey>
        <themekey>Sea surface temperature</themekey>
        <themekey>Transect sampling</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>USGS Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</placekt>
        <placekey>Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Gulf of Alaska</placekey>
        <placekey>Prince William Sound</placekey>
        <placekey>Kenai Peninsula</placekey>
        <placekey>Alaska Peninsula</placekey>
        <placekey>Kachemak Bay</placekey>
      </place>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Kenai Fjords National Park</placekey>
        <placekey>Katmai National Park and Preserve</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>It is requested that the authors and the USGS Alaska Science Center be cited for any subsequent publications that reference this dataset. This material is based upon work funded by the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council under Project/Program No. 12120114-R. Any opinions, findings, conclusions, or recommendations expressed herein are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views or positions of the Trustee Council.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>4210 University Drive</address>
          <city>Anchorage</city>
          <state>Alaska</state>
          <postal>99508</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>907-786-7000</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>ascweb@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Many people (USGS staff, contractors, and volunteers, NPS staff and volunteers, and NOAA staff) contributed to collection of the temperature data contained in this data set. The Nearshore Component Principal Investigators involved in this effort include: Brenda Ballachey, James Bodkin, Heather Coletti, Tom Dean, Dan Esler, Dominic Hondolero, Katrin Iken, Kim Kloecker, Brenda Konar, Dan Monson, Brian Robinson, Sarah Traiger, and Ben Weitzman.</datacred>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Weitzman, B.P.</origin>
        <origin>Konar, B.</origin>
        <origin>Iken, K.</origin>
        <origin>Coletti, H.A.</origin>
        <origin>Monson, D.H.</origin>
        <origin>Suryan, R.</origin>
        <origin>Dean, T.A.</origin>
        <origin>Hondolero, D.</origin>
        <origin>Lindeberg, M.</origin>
        <pubdate>2021</pubdate>
        <title>Changes in Rocky Intertidal Community Structure during a Marine Heatwave in the Northern Gulf of Alaska</title>
        <geoform>journal article</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>Frontiers in Marine Science</sername>
          <issue>8:556820</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>online</pubplace>
          <publish>Frontiers</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <othercit>Weitzman, B.P., Konar, B., Iken, K., Coletti, H.A., Monson, D.H., Suryan, R., Dean, T.A., Hondolero, D., Lindeberg, M., 2021. Changes in rocky intertidal community structure during a marine heatwave in the northern Gulf of Alaska. Frontiers in Marine Science 8:556820.  doi:10.3389/fmars.2021.556820</othercit>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2021.556820</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Traiger, S.B.</origin>
        <origin>Bodkin, J.L.</origin>
        <origin>Coletti, H.A.</origin>
        <origin>Ballachey, B.</origin>
        <origin>Dean, T.</origin>
        <origin>Esler, D.</origin>
        <origin>Iken, K.</origin>
        <origin>Konar, B.</origin>
        <origin>Lindeberg, M.R.</origin>
        <origin>Monson, D.</origin>
        <origin>Robinson, B.</origin>
        <origin>Suryan, R.M.</origin>
        <origin>Weitzman, B.P.</origin>
        <pubdate>2022</pubdate>
        <title>Evidence of Increased Mussel Abundance Related to the Pacific Marine Heatwave and Sea Star Wasting</title>
        <geoform>journal article</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>Marine Ecology</sername>
          <issue>43(3):e12715</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>online</pubplace>
          <publish>Wiley</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <othercit>Traiger, S.B, Bodkin, J.L., Coletti, H.A., Ballachey, B., Dean, T., Esler, D., Iken, K., Konar, B., Lindeberg, M.R., Monson, D., Robinson, B., Suryan, R.M., Weitzman, B.P., 2022. Evidence of increased mussel abundance related to the Pacific marine heatwave and sea star wasting. Marine Ecology 43(3):e12715.  doi:10.1111/maec.12715</othercit>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.1111/maec.12715</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>These are the raw, uncorrected data downloaded directly from the HOBO temperature loggers. Non-deployment times have been clipped from the front and back end of each download. Files were examined for outliers. 

      Calibration procedures began in 2016. HOBOs recovered in 2016 went through a series of calibration soaks in a laboratory controlled water bath at 0, 10 and 20 °C for one hour at each temperature, and logged temperatures were compared with these known water bath temperatures. 

      HOBOs deployed after 2016 went through the same calibration process prior to deployment to assure that all HOBOs were recording temperature values within the manufactures guaranteed accuracy (±0.21°C, see below). Any HOBOs that were not logging temperatures within this level of accuracy were returned to the manufacturer. 

      Published HOBO specifications:
      Temperature Sensor
      Accuracy ±0.21°C from 0° to 50°C (±0.38°F from 32° to 122°F), 
      Resolution 0.02°C at 25°C (0.04°F at 77°F), 
      Response Time (90%) 5 minutes in water; 12 minutes in air moving 2 m/sec (typical)
      Stability (Drift) 0.1°C (0.18°F) per year.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>These are the raw, uncorrected data downloaded directly from the HOBO temperature loggers. False or unexpected temperature values may be present. Data users are advised to examine the data prior to use.</logic>
    <complete>In some years instruments were lost, not deployed, or loggers failed; therefore, there are gaps in data when any of these occurred. There is no .csv file for KATM_2011-2012 because no HOBO loggers were deployed in that year for that block.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Locations for the endpoints of the transect are accurate to within several meters. Most have an accuracy under 15 meters. See the site location data release for rocky site locations: https://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F78S4N3R (Coletti et al. 2017)</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <method>
        <methtype>Field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Temperatures were measured using Hobo Water Temperature Pr v2 Data Loggers - U22-001. These were manufactured by Onset Computer Corp., 470 MacArthur Blvd., Bourne, MA, 02532. Instruments have a reported range of -40 to 70 degrees C in air and -40 to 50 degrees C in water. Instruments are accurate to + or - .21 degrees C over a range of temperatures from 0 to 50 degrees C.</methdesc>
      </method>
      <method>
        <methtype>Field</methtype>
        <methdesc>Temperature loggers were deployed during rocky site sampling in one year and removed for data download approximately one year later using Onset's waterproof shuttle and HOBOware Pro software. Temperature was measured at 0.5 m and 1.5 m Mean Low Low Water (MLLW) elevation at each site and at a few sites at 2.5 m MLLW. The tidal elevations are nominal values and may potentially differ by an estimated maximum of 20 cm from the actual elevation, but were at the same elevation as the nominal sampling locations for intertidal invertebrates and algae. Temperature loggers measured air temperature when tidal levels were below them and water temperature when tidal levels were above them. At one site in each monitoring region, Amalik in the Alaska Peninsula Region, McCarty in the Kenai Peninsula Region, and Whale in western Prince William Sound, an array of temperature loggers was deployed for a year.</methdesc>
      </method>
      <method>
        <methtype>Lab</methtype>
        <methdesc>Calibration procedures began in 2016. Temperature loggers recovered in 2016 went through a series of calibration soaks in a laboratory-controlled water bath at 0, 10 and 20 °C for one hour at each temperature, and logged temperatures were compared with these known water bath temperatures. Temperature loggers deployed since 2016 undergo the same calibration process before deployment and after retrieval. Those not recording temperature values within the manufactures guaranteed accuracy (±0.21°C) prior to deployment were not used.

        The temperature loggers deployed at Kaflia from July 2014 to July 2015 returned temperatures approximately 2.6 °C lower than the temperature loggers deployed at the same site immediately before and after it. The calibration procedures also found an average difference of -2.6 °C. Similarly, the temperature logger deployed at Kaflia from July 2015 to July 2016 was found to have and average difference of -0.85 °C during the post-deployment calibration procedure. This same temperature logger was deployed at Iktua from June 2014 to June 2015. We have corrected those temperature readings by adding 2.6 degrees C and 0.85 degrees C as appropriate. For the affected files, only the corrected temperature values are provided.</methdesc>
      </method>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Monson, D.H.</origin>
            <origin>Kloecker, K.A.</origin>
            <origin>Ballachey, B.E.</origin>
            <origin>Bodkin, J.L.</origin>
            <origin>Coletti, H.A.</origin>
            <origin>Dean, T.A.</origin>
            <origin>Esler, D.</origin>
            <origin>Esslinger, G.G.</origin>
            <origin>Paszalek, J.</origin>
            <origin>Weitzman, B.P.</origin>
            <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
            <title>Gulf Watch Alaska Benthic Component: Marine Water Quality, Water Temperature from Prince William Sound, Katmai National Park and Preserve, and Kenai Fjords National Park, 2006-2014</title>
            <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Anchorage, AK</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Monson, D.H. Kloecker, K.A. Ballachey, B.E. Bodkin, J.L. Coletti, H.A. Dean, T.A. Esler, D., Esslinger, G.G. Paszalek, J. Weitzman, B.P., 2016. Gulf Watch Alaska Benthic Component: Marine Water Quality, Water Temperature from Prince William Sound, Katmai National Park and Preserve, and Kenai Fjords National Park, 2006-2014: U.S. Geological Survey data release, https://doi.org/10.5066/F7WH2N3T</othercit>
            <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/F7WH2N3T</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>document</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>2016</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Monson et al. 2016</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Previously published water temperature data (2006-2014) which are now included in this data release.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Monson, D.H.</origin>
            <origin>Kloecker, K.A.</origin>
            <pubdate>2017</pubdate>
            <title>Marine Water Quality, Water Temperature from Prince William Sound, Katmai National Park and Preserve, and Kenai Fjords National Park, 2014-2016</title>
            <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Anchorage, AK</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Monson, D.H., Kloecker, K.A., 2017. Gulf Watch Alaska Nearshore Component: Marine Water Quality, Water Temperature from Prince William Sound, Katmai National Park and Preserve, and Kenai Fjords National Park, 2014-2016: U.S. Geological Survey data release, https://doi.org/10.5066/F77S7KXH</othercit>
            <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/F77S7KXH</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>document</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>2017</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Monson and Kloecker 2017</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Previously published water temperature data (2014-2016) which are now included in this data release.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Dean, T.A.</origin>
            <origin>Bodkin, J.L.</origin>
            <pubdate>2011</pubdate>
            <title>SOP for sampling of intertidal invertebrates and algae on sheltered rocky shores - Version 4.6</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>Natural Resource Report NPS/SWAN/NRR</sername>
              <issue>2011/397</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Fort Collins, Colorado</pubplace>
              <publish>National Park Service</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Dean, T.A., Bodkin, J.L., 2011. SOP for sampling of intertidal invertebrates and algae on sheltered rocky shores - Version 4.6: Southwest Alaska Inventory and Monitoring Network. Natural Resource Report NPS/SWAN/NRR - 2011/397. National Park Service, Fort Collins, Colorado.

            Published report archived by U.S. National Park Service Catalog (IRMA Data Store) https://irma.nps.gov/DataStore [reference code: 2170950]</othercit>
            <onlink>https://irma.nps.gov/DataStore/Reference/Profile/2170950</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>Digital Report</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>2011</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Dean and Bodkin 2011</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Sampling protocol used for sampling Rocky intertidal invertebrates and algae at each study site.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Dean, T.A.</origin>
            <origin>Bodkin, J.L.</origin>
            <origin>Coletti, H.</origin>
            <pubdate>2014</pubdate>
            <title>Protocol Narrative for Nearshore Marine Ecosystem Monitoring in the Gulf of Alaska - Version 1.1</title>
            <geoform>report</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>Natural Resource Report NPS/SWAN/NRR</sername>
              <issue>2014/756</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Fort Collins, Colorado</pubplace>
              <publish>National Park Service</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Dean, T. A., Bodkin, J. L., Coletti, H. A., 2014. Protocol narrative for marine nearshore ecosystem monitoring in the Gulf of Alaska - Version 1.1. Natural Resource Report NPS/SWAN/NRR— 2014/756. National Park Service, Fort Collins, Colorado.

            Published report archived by U.S. National Park Service Catalog (IRMA Data Store) https://irma.nps.gov/DataStore [reference code: 2206501]</othercit>
            <onlink>https://irma.nps.gov/DataStore/Reference/Profile/2206501</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>Digital Report</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>2014</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Dean et al. 2014</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Naming convention for site ID and site name for each study site sampling location.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Coletti, H.A.</origin>
            <origin>Kloecker, K.A.</origin>
            <origin>Bodkin, J.L.</origin>
            <origin>Dean, T.A.</origin>
            <pubdate>2017</pubdate>
            <title>Gulf Watch Alaska Nearshore Component: Monitoring Site Locations from Prince William Sound, Katmai National Park and Preserve, and Kenai Fjords National Park</title>
            <geoform>tabular digital data</geoform>
            <serinfo>
              <sername>U.S. Geological Survey Data Release</sername>
              <issue>10.5066/F78S4N3R</issue>
            </serinfo>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Anchorage, Alaska</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <othercit>Coletti, H.A., Kloecker, K.A., Bodkin, J.L., Dean, T.A., 2017. Gulf Watch Alaska Nearshore Component: Monitoring Site Locations from Prince William Sound, Katmai National Park and Preserve, and Kenai Fjords National Park: U.S. Geological Survey data release, https://doi.org/10.5066/F78S4N3R</othercit>
            <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/F78S4N3R</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>document</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>
              <caldate>2017</caldate>
            </sngdate>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>Coletti et al. 2017</srccitea>
        <srccontr>Geographic coordinates of sampling sites</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data were downloaded from the HOBO temperature loggers using Onset's waterproof shuttle and HOBOware Pro software.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data were edited to remove temperatures recorded before or after deployment in the field as well as anomalous readings outside of expected temperature bounds.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>New columns were appended to the columns directly output from the temperature loggers. The newly added columns were: 'block', 'site', 'tide_height', 'position', and 'HOBO_ID'. See entity/attribute section for definitions of these columns.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Dean and Bodkin 2011</srcused>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>HOBO temperature reading (degrees Celsius) standardized to 30-minute intervals (on the hour and half hour). Most HOBOs were programed to record temperature every 30-minutes. However, in early years temperature logging intervals were 20, 30 or 60-minutes. When temperature was logged at intervals other than every 30 minutes, interpolation was used to estimate the value at 30-minute intervals.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Dean and Bodkin 2011</srcused>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>We added predicted tide height. The predicted tide heights were determined using the Tide and Currents software (Nobeltec, https://mdnautical.com/) and the tide station nearest each site. List of site/tide station pairings:
        KATM Amalik Bay site = Takli Island tide station;
        KATM Kinak Bay site = Takli Island tide station;
        KATM Takli Island site = Takli Island tide station;
        KATM Kaflia Bay site = Kukak Bay tide station;
        KATM Kukak Bay site = Kukak Bay tide station;
        KEFJ Aialik Bay site = Aialik Sill tide station;
        KEFJ Harris Bay site = Upper NW Fjords tide station;
        KEFJ McCarty Lagoon site = Chance Cove tide station;
        KEFJ Nuka Bay site = Nuka Bay tide station;
        KEFJ Nuka Pass site = Nuka Pass tide station;
        WPWS Herring Bay site = Herring Point tide station;
        WPWS Hogan Bay site = Hogan Bay tide station;
        WPWS Iktua Bay site = Guguak tide station;
        WPWS Johnson Bay site = Port Audrey tide station;
        WPWS Whale Bay site = Chenega tide station;
        NPWS Cedar Bay site = Glacier Island tide station;
        NPWS Esther Passage site = Culross Bay tide station;
        NPWS Bettles Bay site = Culross Bay tide station;
        NPWS Perry Island site = Applegate tide station;
        EPWS Galena Bay site = Rocky Point tide station;
        EPWS Port Fidalgo site = Landlocked tide station;
        EPWS Olsen Bay site = Port Gravina tide station;
        EPWS Simpson Bay site = Hawkins Island tide station;
        EPWS Observation Island site = Orca Inlet tide station;
        KBAY Bishop Beach site = Anchor Point tide station;
        KBAY Bluff Point site = Anchor Point tide station;
        KBAY Cohen Island site = Homer tide station;
        KBAY Elephant Island site = Homer tide station;
        KBAY Outside Beach site = Seldovia tide station;
        KBAY Port Graham site = Port Graham tide station</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Air vs. water temperature readings were determined from the predicted tidal elevation at the time of the temperature reading and the tide height at which the logger was deployed. A temperature reading was considered water temperature when the predicted tidal elevation was at least 0.5 m higher than the tide height at which the logger was deployed. A temperature reading was considered air temperature when the predicted tidal elevation was at least 0.5 m lower than the tide height at which the logger was deployed. A temperature reading was considered a transition temperature when the predicted tidal elevation was within 0.5 m of the tide height at which the logger was deployed.</procdesc>
        <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <indspref>The only spatial information in these data are the named locations for the sampling sites. Sites are documented with start and end coordinates and are also referred to by site name (e.g., Herring Bay rocky sampling site). Please refer to Coletti et al. 2017, a USGS data release which provides for geographic coordinates of all sites: https://doi.org/10.5066/F78S4N3R</indspref>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>0.00000001</latres>
        <longres>0.00000001</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>World Geodetic System of 1984 (WGS84)</horizdn>
        <ellips>World Geodetic System of 1984 (WGS84)</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Intertidal_Temperature_[BLOCK]_[YYY1]-[YYY2].csv</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Six folders with tables of water and air temperature data. Each folder contains data from one sampling "Block" (KBAY, KEFJ, NPWS, WPWS, EPWS, KATM), as defined in Coletti et al. 2017. Within folders, there is a table for each sample year (i.e., from June 1st of one year to May 31st the following year). Presented in a Comma Separated Value (CSV) formatted tables.

        Filenaming convention: [BLOCK] is the name of the sampling "block", [YYY1] is the deployment year, [YYY2] is the download year.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Author defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>block</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Name of sampling block within each sampling region, as defined in Coletti et al 2017, https://doi.org/10.5066/F78S4N3R</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Coletti et al. 2017</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>KBAY</edomv>
            <edomvd>Kachemak Bay (Block 04, Region = Kenai Peninsula)</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>KEFJ</edomv>
            <edomvd>Kenai Fjords National Park (Block 05, Region = Kenai Peninsula)</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>NPWS</edomv>
            <edomvd>Northern Prince William Sound (Block 07; Region = Prince William Sound)</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>WPWS</edomv>
            <edomvd>Western Prince William Sound (Block 08; Region = Prince William Sound)</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>EPWS</edomv>
            <edomvd>Eastern Prince William Sound (Block 09, Region = Prince William Sound)</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>KATM</edomv>
            <edomvd>Katmai National Park (Block 10, Region = Alaska Peninsula)</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>site</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Name of sampling site within each sampling block, as defined in Coletti et al 2017, https://doi.org/10.5066/F78S4N3R.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Coletti et al. 2017</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Name of sampling sites within each sampling block</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>date</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Date (YYYY-MM-DD) of temperature reading.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Date of temperature reading corresponding to the range of years presented by each table.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>time</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Time (24-hr) of temperature reading, local time (UTC -8 h).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Time of temperature reading (HH:mm).</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>sensor</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Name for the temperature logger position. A concatenation of 'site_name' (Coletti et al. 2017), 'tide_height', and 'position'. Example: "Fidalgo_0.5a"</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Name for the temperature logger position.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>HOBO_ID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Unique ID of each HOBO temperature logger, assigned by the manufacturer. Instruments were re-deployed after download, and therefore not unique to a single site or year. HOBO IDs listed as "-9999999" indicates that the ID number is unknown.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Onset (https://www.onsetcomp.com/)</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Unique ID of each HOBO temperature logger, assigned by the manufacturer.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>tide_height</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Tidal elevation of temperature logger. The vertical height (in meters) above mean lower low water (MLLW). Temperature loggers were set at 0.5 m, 1.5 m, and 2.5 m above MLLW. The "standard" tidal elevation (with longest time-series) is 0.5 m. Since 2014, temperature loggers have also been deployed at 1.5 m. Additionally, for one sample year (2014-2015), temperature loggers were deployed at 2.5 m.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>0.5</edomv>
            <edomvd>0.5 meters above MLLW</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>1.5</edomv>
            <edomvd>1.5 meters above MLLW</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>2.5</edomv>
            <edomvd>2.5 meters above MLLW</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>position</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The position of the temperature logger along the intertidal sampling transect (start, middle, end). Middle and end positions were only used at the 0.5 meter tidal elevation for one year (2014-2015).</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>a</edomv>
            <edomvd>Standard position at start of the transect line</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>b</edomv>
            <edomvd>Midpoint along the transect line</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>c</edomv>
            <edomvd>End of the transect line</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>tidelevl</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Predicted tide level (meters) at the time of the temperature reading. Tide prediction taken from Tides and Currents program using the nearest tide station to the site. See processing steps for a list of tide station locations.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Predicted tide level (meters) at the time of the temperature reading.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>exposure</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>An indicator for the type of temperature reading listed in the "temperature" attribute.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>air</edomv>
            <edomvd>Air when the predicted tidal elevation was at least 0.5 m lower than the tide height at which the logger was deployed. Temperature logger readings (degrees Celsius) at 30-minute intervals.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>transition</edomv>
            <edomvd>Transition when the predicted tidal elevation was within 0.5 m of the tide height at which the logger was deployed. Temperature logger readings (degrees Celsius) at 30-minute intervals.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>water</edomv>
            <edomvd>Water when the predicted tidal elevation was at least 0.5 m higher than the tide height at which the logger was deployed. Temperature logger readings (degrees Celsius) at 30-minute intervals.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>air/transition</edomv>
            <edomvd>Air and transition when the tidal elevation and tide height do not match the parameters for air or transition temperature and the temperature reading does not align with water temperature.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Author defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>temperature</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Temperature logger readings (degrees Celsius) at 30-minute intervals. Most values are raw uncorrected readings downloaded directly from the temperature loggers. In cases where the temperature was logged at intervals other than 30 minutes, the value is an estimate based on interpolation.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Temperature logger readings (degrees Celsius) at 30-minute intervals.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>KBAYKATMKEFJWPWS_2006-2023_intertidalTemperature_Contributors.csv</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Table with a list of principal investigators and contributors to this dataset. Presented in a Comma Separated Value (CSV) formatted tables.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Author defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Last_Name</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The last name of a Gulf Watch Alaska contributor.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>The last name of a Gulf Watch Alaska contributor.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>First_Name</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The first name of a Gulf Watch Alaska contributor.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>The first name of a Gulf Watch Alaska contributor.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ORCID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The ORCID (Open Researcher and Contributor ID) for each collaborator. The null values "." indicate that the contributor does not have an ORCID or the ID is unknown.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>The ORCID (Open Researcher and Contributor ID) for each collaborator.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Position</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The position title of the Gulf Watch Alaska contributor.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>The position title of the Gulf Watch Alaska contributor.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Agency</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The agency who the Gulf Watch Alaska contributor is associated with.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>The agency who the Gulf Watch Alaska contributor is associated with.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Program</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The program within the agency who the Gulf Watch Alaska contributor is associated with. The null values "." indicate that the program of the collaborator is unknown.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Author defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>The program within the agency who the Gulf Watch Alaska contributor is associated with.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>4210 University Drive</address>
          <city>Anchorage</city>
          <state>Alaska</state>
          <postal>99508</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>907-786-7000</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>ascweb@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>The U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center is the authoritative source and distributor of these data.</resdesc>
    <distliab>Unless otherwise stated, all data, metadata and related materials are considered to satisfy the quality standards relative to the purpose for which the data were collected. Although these data and associated metadata have been reviewed for accuracy and completeness and approved for release by the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data for other purposes or on all computer systems, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>CSV</formname>
          <formcont>Data are distributed in a Zip package containing data in CSV format and FGDC metadata in XML and HTML formats.</formcont>
          <filedec>Compression applied by the 7-Zip utility using the default compression level [5]. The Zip package can be decompressed and unpacked by open source or commercially available unzip tools.</filedec>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/F7WH2N3T</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>None</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20220918</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Alaska Science Center</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>4210 University Drive</address>
          <city>Anchorage</city>
          <state>Alaska</state>
          <postal>99508</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>907-786-7000</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>ascweb@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata (CSDGM)</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>